Jose Ensevce, not so fast El Jefe. Jose himself is a 2012 inductee of the Hall
of Fame.
First Hispanic public official in the history of the city of Cleveland. White
House fellow in the Reagan administration.
He's practiced law and led the Puerto Rican and broader Hispanic communities
for decades.
He has earned the title that his son is called him of El Jefe. So let's get the
boss up here in the duck system.
Yes, I know there's a singer by that name. Alright.
Anyway, I counted a joy and a privilege to introduce my dear friend of more
than 60 years.
You heard that right, more than 60 years, Sister Alicia Alvarado.
I'm happy to do that on behalf of our community, especially my organization in
Hispanic Roundtable that's sitting over there.
Well, I'm only going to be able to scratch the surface of her accomplishments
and character.
I'd like to give you a little flavor of the life of this dynamic young Latina,
Sister Alicia Alvarado.
So let me give you a brief description of what I hope to cover here.
She's a faithful servant of her God and King. She's the first daughter of the
Hispanic community.
Servant leader, grassroots leader, and a friend of all, especially the poor.
Sister was born in Puerto Rico. She grew up on the Midwest side of Cleveland on
the West 31st place.
She attended St. Patrick's School where she was educated by the personal nuns
and influenced by the Jesuit priests.
And that's where she got her initial call to the Sisterhood.
She was the devoted child of her mother, Lorna Rosa, and Don Felipe, and her
brothers and sisters, especially her development of the challenge sister.
But her guiding principles and priorities were always God first, her family
second, the poor, the needy in the weak, and the community were third.
And Alicia was last, always a distant last.
In our community, she was involved in every, let me underline, every major
Hispanic organization and initiative.
Let me give you a little flavor.
She began her involvement with the Puerto Rican, well, PR 76.
And then she went to the Spanish American committee and always was one of the
principal leaders there.
And she served there for decades, decades, serving the underserved.
Where she always served the underserved for food, housing, and work.
In 1984, what was the other Hispanic forum, another Hispanic roundtable, she
helped convene the entirety of our community at San Ignatius High School where
we set our first agenda.
So I remember in 1984, those many late nights in the Justice Center, my former
office, the city of Cleveland Press Museum's office with Jose Feña Nueva, with
Jose Feña and Sister Alicia, and trying to plan our event.
And I can remember always saying to Alicia, how do we know anyone?
And she always said, she always assured me, she said, my people will come. And
they did.
And so at this first event at Ignatius, we had thousands, thousands of people
that showed up.
And the person that's most responsible for that initial success was sitting
right over here.
And they came because Sister Alicia Alvarado asked her to come.
Because there's no better community organizer in this community because of her
big love, because of her big heart, and the love of our community for Sister
Alicia.
The little flavor for this historic accomplishment, just to digress a little
bit, but among the first things that we did there was that Alicia was a big
supporter of this, was the Hispanic scholarship forum, which is Esperanza,
which today gives more than a hundred scholarships.
And it is one of the largest Hispanic scholarship programs and most successful
in this country, and the person that has made as big a contribution as anyone
to sit right over there.
So that community participation tradition exists to this very day.
And I'll explain to you in our last convention recording, we had 3,000 people.
3,000 people attended.
And that, approximately the cause of that, is sitting right over there. I mean,
that is such a big deal.
Did you know who goes there? Dick Pomer! Pomer goes over there. That's how big
that is.
Anyway, Sister Alicia loves her culture, and I'm reminded of the Puerto Rican
composer, roughly every night, as we said, "If I had not been born Puerto Rican,
I would have wished I had been born Puerto Rican."
Anyway, that's Sister Alicia. And it's a core sentiment in Alicia's life.
So she loves our food, the rice and beans, the bienvene, the roc
compoi, or the patina, the flan, the pada deja, the marcida, and a sofada. That's
just where she started.
But, what that has to be associated with music, principally in berengue and
salsa, and dancing.
And boy, can that girl dance. So you've heard of the flying nun and the singing
nun,
but you're shortly going to meet a dancing nun.
She's always made a profound sense of social justice, and that was manifested
with her work with the beloved and historic Cesar Childress.
And his efforts and their efforts to, on behalf of Farmworker Movement, to help
them attain a decent life for all farmworkers throughout America.
When Chavez was here, Sister drove him throughout the entire state, and she was
Cesar Chavez's chauffeur.
And Cesar Chavez used to refer to her as his bodyguard here in Ohio.
And she played a significant role in people politics. She was intimately
involved in Charles Stokes's two elections.
Stokes, of course, was the first African American mayor of a major city in
America.
Moreover, she campaigned and worked, and principally was responsible for the
election of Joe Santiago,
who served admirably as his administrative assistant.
But she also shared her gifts with her American sisters, where she served on
their national board as well.
And that is as a result of her humility, her leadership gifts, and her love of
the Lord.
About ten years ago, she suffered a massive stroke, and I remember seeing her
at her rehab facility in the fetal position,
and unable to speak. And truthfully, I did not believe that she was going to
survive.
But there are modern day miracles, and God in His goodness gave her back to us
because He still had more for her to do.
But let me finish with a couple of scripture quotes that come to mind when I
think of Sister Alicia.
The first is in the Old Testament, to do it around me. "You shall walk after
the Lord your God, and you shall serve Him and hold fast to Him."
And from my end of the Testament, James 2.
"But what good is it, my brothers, if someone says that He has faith, but He
does not have works?
If your brother or sister is poorly clothed and lacking in daily food, and one
of you says, 'Then go and peace be warmed and filled without giving them the
things needed for the body,' what good is that?"
God has a special focus on the poor, the words of the evangelist Luke,
regarding principles in Sister Alicia's life.
"What you've done for the least of my brethren, you've done for me." So she has
lived her faith and served our God by serving others.
So let me give you this great servant leader, this patron saint of the Hispanic
community, this bodyguard, this friend of all, especially the weak and the poor,
the dancing nun, Elmara Alicia Barad.
[applause]